We have to know
that truth is what it is.
We cannot conceptualize it
with our human awareness.
We cannot order it.
We cannot manipulate it.
We cannot organize it.
It is what it is, has been, and will be.
And what is the truth?
Truth is that we are surrounded,
or we are penetrated,
or we are nourished,
looked after and loved,
by a very subtle energy
which is the energy of Divine love.
The second truth is
that we are not this body,
this mind,
these conditionings,
this ego,
but we are the Spirit.
You don't have to accept what I am saying blindly,
because blind faith leads to fanaticism.
But as scientists, you must keep your mind open
and see for yourself what I am saying.
If it is so, honestly you must accept it.
We know so much through science
about our civilisation,
our advancement.
This is the advancement of a tree
which has grown outside very much.
But if we do not know our roots,
we'll be destroyed.
So it is important to know about our roots.
And this is what it is,
that I would say are our roots.
As you can see there are seven centres within us
and these subtle centres are placed
in the spinal cord and in the brain.
These cater to our physical, mental,
emotional, and spiritual needs.
On the physical side, they manifest
the energy for the use of our plexuses
which look after our physical problems.
That is on the right side.
This energy which is supplied by this yellow line,
a subtle channel, we call it as the Pingala Nadi.
This supplies energy for our physical
and mental actions.
So this is the power of action within us
which also caters
to the right sympathetic nervous system.
The another channel you see on the left hand side
is the channel by which we desire.
Put our energy to our desire.
So this is the power of desire
and looks after our emotions.
This is the one which
looks after our conditionings, also.
At the end of these two channels they create
two institutions.
One on the right side crosses over,
and the yellow balloon that you see is the ego.
Is the balloon of ego that we have.
And the left-hand side one,
which conditions our mind,
is the balloon of superego.
As we start growing in age,
by the time we are 12 years of age,
these two completely meet
and the soft bone in our head becomes
completely calcified.
Now there is a third energy within us
which is in the centre.
And this central energy is the one
which has made us human beings,
and these centres are the milestones
of our evolution.
So now the last jumping is left out.
It has reached up to the limbic area.
Now, only thing, it has to break through
the soft bone on the head
and break through that.